back in the day so much absolutely
should we start where we started then
because we both met or we all met at gnc
didn't we yeah dom you started way
before that in fitness and then yeah i
sort of came into pt only just before
you did it literally
yeah yeah i was like
2010 but 2012 in norway norwich moved up
here
started at the gym group um oh tell them
the story i like the story you like this
one
300 pounds in your pocket
[Music]
as she was walking down the aisle
it was like didn't you bring me a kettle
or something
like a basic white skilled [\h__\h] yeah
anyway whatever yeah so um
yeah i moved up here with 500 quid and
then um
yeah just
started the gym group
literally like had like no money about
three months in and then uh i did
obviously i got the job at gnc um
yeah which was which was the start of
that for me
and then yeah it just sort of snowballed
from there like obviously i think i
think it's a good um place for a pt to
start is
the gym group yeah or a pure gym
like i know i've got my own gym and i'm
a you know i prefer now once you're once
you've got yourself there working from a
you know more private quieter gym's good
but the footfall you get as a pt yeah so
four pure gyms and the gym groups
yeah but we're calling budget gyms yeah
yeah it's so good for pts up and coming
pt's just qualified i don't know what
they do now but when i was there you
you just done three hours for the gym
yeah and you didn't pay you went i don't
know it's the same
so for me like
that's great like you're not outlaying
money
and you've got
access to what thousands i think when i
was at the gym yeah the one in one in
norwich they had like
5 000 members when i was at a peak and
that's
that's a lot of footfall um coming
through the door and i think as long as
you're
going around talking to people making
yourself like
known saying hello to people is probably
the big one yeah
yeah you've got it you've got to be
social like just try and hide away and
expect people to come to like look at
the pt board with the signs and
you know
yes
especially as well i think like
qualifications we need them
but like some people just
overload in my opinion on qualifications
[Music]
um i left after two years and went to a
uh worked in a crossfit gym
not doing crossfit but just
for the record for the director
yeah um we love crossfit yeah um but
yeah so i worked there um they got
really busy which was good for them so i
then left
uh bounced around a few other gyms and
then just
kind of wanted to work myself and have
like i kind of wanted to look after
other pts in the industry who had kind
of been messed about by other gym owners
because it can be quite a volatile area
but um yeah and then sort of set up my
own place and then we moved again
and then we are where we are now so it's
uh it's yeah it's
been a long journey yeah what was
happening
what was the course like when you did it
way back then i did mine i actually did
an online course yeah wow i did my level
two with uh
i think it was through the ymca oh yeah
um back in sort of cambridge and then uh
i went online i can't actually remember
who i worked with um so i did like i
think about 19 months of online
and then i went to
david lloyd's in
ipswich yeah and uh i was the closest
person to ipswich about an hour and a
half away
the closest person had to wait till last
to do their tests like their physical
exam
oh yeah she didn't do it before i got
there you just stood
woman was like yeah well now do you you
will do your exam your practical exam so
yeah we were there until like four got
home like half five and
that was all good passed on the day and
stuff but um
yeah that was a lot of yeah just
reading online there's something which
is a good way of doing it i'd
i'd probably have preferred more
practical stuff yeah um but i think at
the time when i was doing that i was
working at the gym so i was lucky that i
could go see him outside a little bit
yeah and i could i had the access to
have to still practice techniques and
all the sort of stuff they teach and
stuff so yeah that was good but um yeah
it's kind of that was out for me there
and then obviously just leading up to
where we are now pretty much for 10
years this year so yeah yeah where are
you now like tell them
well obviously you've got my own gym so
uh obviously
that's that's the end goal
but yeah like i i went in i went into
business with a visit with a friend of
mine and then it didn't really work out
massively for them um so i sort of we
kind of have a business partner and then
uh i sort of brought him out because he
had other ventures fences he wanted to
go into so i just basically took off
myself nice um took it on myself and uh
still pt still pt so yeah
got a couple of therapists as well
a couple of other pts who work here
always room for more
but yeah where are we where are we
inside so we're down around roundtree
way
[Music]
before that was like a warehouse gym you
think it's going to be great as a pt
it's so cold yeah yeah that's brutal man
like it's like naught degrees outside
it's like -2 in the gym are you thinking
like i remember when i was when i was at
the you know the old gym when it was
called evolution before i moved and made
ironside we had
a day i drove down the mdr
in snow in the mrs carr i had one guy
who said i'll make it.
and i was like i will get there i got
stuck on the ndr i had spayed i had to
dig myself out of snow just to get to
work
my client didn't come
and we trained and i had the gym open
like for about three hours and i went
i'm just going home
so that was the beast
from the east i remember that because i
was i was living in the city just down
deer road it was only normally 15 20
minute walk straight line for me and i'm
putting beanbags in my shoes and they
should feed down yeah i slipped
only to come in had five people booked
in sorry i can't make it sorry yes
three four years has ruined my blood
flow to my fingers and toes but um
yeah i think yeah i think it makes you
learn a lot about becoming a pt that
sort of stuff like
also the hours getting up early
like i didn't necessarily say to people
like don't expect to come into this
industry and think that nine to five
yeah it's great like eventually you
might get to a stage where you can go
you know what
i can be scientists what i've got like
if you build your client base up and you
pick up clients who own their own
business i've got a few now coming at
nine coming at ten you're coming up like
one coming at four and you think this is
good but i've still got clients at seven
i've still got clients like eight till
nine at night you you know if i see your
instagram half the time you're it's like
10 o'clock at night and i'm sat there
with a cup of tea
i know i've been at work 14 hours
through that man
but then again you probably rolling at
like 12
like you'd rather probably do like 11 12
till
whatever and you've got a little you
know if you you can you can cater it to
yourself yeah you can do like you can
certainly do that so um
yeah especially like i say if you go
back to working out like say the the
budget gyms
being a clientele base some of them are
coming in during the day and if they
want pt you're thinking well actually if
i want to build a business on nine to
five that's a prime client so yeah what
about you
so you know what this is this is the
epic tale that dom is going to love
so
i can even tell you what year
all right
2013.
so i step into g and c
if if if you don't know what gnc was
just google it it was a sports nutrition
shop pothole
of fitness in norwich it really was you
had
mpts coming in
asking what they can do or take to get
bigger stronger leaner they had they
then sent their clients in with lists do
you remember the lists
you know i need this yeah yeah my pt
said i need this i need this um and it
was brilliant you know game owners will
come in and do some stock for their own
fridges we was it was brilliant and to
be honest that
that was probably one of the happiest
times of my life
yeah it was a nice little community
have a chat yeah they would wait for the
pre-work time
i think a tub got you through 10 days
yes you buy a mug sweat for 120 quid
then you advice fat burners
the box of card killers
and i was just sort of sat there like
the first time you came and i was like
who's this dude and justin was just like
how's this beardy he just comes in
[Music]
and you know what it's
that i got in that way like so i was a
massive consumer
of the industry
and
i was trying to do a bodybuilding show
it's 23 23 yeah
um
and
it was it was hilariously
i was hilariously honest it was your
tuner and rice ah and i was i was tired
i was wasting money on supplements like
these guys felt so sorry for me they
would give me stuff discount everything
and then dom tells me that he's a coach
and he actually you gave me your your
guidance
three four months for absolutely
free yes it's the first time like it was
the first time i'd ever like
took someone through a bodybuilding show
yeah i was like yeah yeah let's have a
go at this yeah yeah yeah
it was it was yeah i remember it like i
remember it well i remember you you come
in sunflower oil tinned tuna oh
rice like three times a day the protein
shake stereotypical society
all that google would have told me
that could have been worse free fish and
rice diet fish rice cakes
but yeah i was um
yeah i was amazed and then yeah it was a
that was a fun one i i remember like
that was about a week out you rang me
and you were like
i can't do it i was like you said i just
thinking
a pack
the day you competed you didn't have
enough tan and i'm stood at the top you
remember this over you heard this i was
stood at the top of the i don't really
thought that building in yarmouth was
called i didn't know what it was and
literally
into your groin
oh died it was that was yeah but that
was a big learning curve so that was for
me as well for me as well and that's to
be honest seeing how well you coached me
and all the stuff that i didn't know
that i thought i knew this is the best
thing
once you get qualified oh my god will it
ground you yeah it will ground you um
and from that i actually quit my
it was i think my
you know
yeah i was working for seo sofas um top
salesman sales manager you're like big
money
35 grand a year yeah i think you said
even something like bonuses like 40k
that's why i had to spare money for gnc
um but yeah quit that to be the saturday
guy
at gnc yeah i remember
that that showed like to me that's a
passion that yeah and that's what got me
in the interest i i i think that's
something i see like
i see people become qualified
and i think the main thing is
like you said that's your grounding you
become qualified and you go wow okay
i've got so much more to learn yeah 100
i think for you that was it though you
learned so much once you're qualified
and you're how many
when did you qualify
because it's
like seven years ago now yeah yeah so
like you guys are like but you've been
going this long yeah yeah survived
it survived the pandemic it's mad it's
like this
um
yeah like i think that's the thing like
your show's a passion and you have to
have a passion to do this so
um
yeah like i think when i worked at the
gym with so many people so like petey's
in and then out and in an hour and
nowadays just like whatever yeah yeah
yeah yeah so it was a case of i went
through something called the training
room
um
and to be fair the thing that made that
enjoyable for me was
the tutor yeah
and genuinely i i appreciated him more
because he had been in the industry yeah
because sometimes you just get tutors
that
that's just academically good
and they're not physically good
especially if it's colleges because
sometimes you'll just get other pets he
should come through this yeah yeah
literally just because he's got the
quals he comes in and he gives you
equals yeah but you miss out on so much
of the practical side of the the big
element of knowing what happens on the
ground yeah and i think that's why
we all get on really well because we've
got that common interest of we are all
the men on the ground yeah i think
that's the thing i think that's the
thing like
with the qualifications nowadays it
looks better for a qualification company
if they just party oh yeah of course
yeah they throw numbers through
absolutely i i've heard of i've heard of
i've heard of pt's like qualification
companies should we say who will message
if they gave say you said if they've not
kept their under the bargain and they'll
give a they'll uh they get given a four
out of five stars for the quality of
what their company's given
like
you get the company message them can you
change it to five stars i've heard of
this happening now i'm thinking
clearly you've not held up your end of
the party yeah yeah and like when you
obviously said you know obviously how
are you setting up your own company i
was like man respect because you know
it's going to be run away this is it
this is i was well pleased
that's also why i didn't want to stop
training i'll still have clients every
day every week because students need to
have the stories to back up the theory
so it's one thing to say oh yeah make
sure you memorize this bit of textbooks
this will come up in the exam where it
needs to be like you need to learn this
or at least know where to find it
because i remember when i had my first
client and they said this i need to know
this or i need to go find out so then
they did so they didn't do that move
forward i think i think that's the thing
as well you see some people set up the
companies
and because they stop training clients
themselves they kind of forget
you lose that ear to the ground you do
yeah they forget what they should be
doing and you just
especially in this industry because it
are we know it is so fast-paced in the
last two years
everything's changing online coaching a
lot of people before right now it was
like yeah here's an excel spreadsheet i
have a chat here once a month
i reckon if i had no
no less than like two years out of the
game and then try to come back to it i
know it'd be different
it's the science as well isn't it yeah
yeah yeah yeah absolutely if you don't
keep up with it
the amount of stuff that i when i first
qualified to what now i look back and
think i'm really saying
yeah
but yeah so what um what have you guys
gone on to do since you got called um
have you gone to our other knowledge
based stuff or you just been picking
stuff up online um
to be fair
um
when i come out of
the the training room i got extra calls
in nutrition yeah
and obviously we've got that sort of
rough element of sports nutrition
we did get configurations yeah a level
equivalents weren't they yeah pretty
much um i couldn't tell you where they
are
so yeah i came into the industry at
quite a high level anyway out of class
that i do cross myself as an elite pt
um like there's nothing wrong with like
picking yourself up i think that's the
problem with a lot of people
pts
they don't think they're good enough
again this is one issue with budget gyms
you go in and every pt is trying to
underdo the other one yeah and i'm
always turning around if any pt sort of
say to me what's in charge i'll have to
sit down and talk to them about that but
then i'll just turn around and say that
look in the day
buy cheap buy twice so you know across
everything yeah yeah yeah yeah like and
just make sure that you know you're
you're
if you're charging more and you have a
list of what you give someone just make
sure you stick to it yeah that's
basically it but it's it's like duties
like you say like who you're trying now
they're charging 20 quid an hour which
you know we know phil i mean yeah yeah
yeah i remember watching uh listening to
a thing about reading the poster i feel
like
um if you become a pt great go follow
the is it at the pt coach yeah he's pc
coach
we both did aca because
yeah we did that so we've done the aca
so that's once you become a pt with
someone like your company the aca like
goes more in depth and you have like
there's a nutrition module there's
business
business and then there's like marketing
and
it goes in depth um
but with something like that he put a
post out on instagram saying like when
he first started charging in he was sort
of like cumbria or something yeah yeah
he was up north yeah
essentially he
when he first started charging as a pt
it was like 25 30 quid it's like 30
years ago and i now see pt's charging 25
quid a session and i'm going 30 years
ago someone in the middle of the arsenal
nowhere not a city was charging that fee
and i think when again london prices but
when he when he finished
pt for the past few years his last
finishing rate for the past three or
four years before he retires at pt
without vad
was 250 quid a session this is in
mayfair in london
but you're looking at like near and
nearly getting up to 300 pounds session
an hour and he said that was without
nutrition he would charge extra for
nutrition this is it yeah we're going to
go so you've got all the goodies so yeah
yeah
you know in march you're not going to be
charging that we know but i think like
yeah you've got to like maybe do some
market research and just value yourself
you've just got a qualification you're
taking someone's else's health into your
hands absolutely like own that yeah i
think people play the wrong game people
come into it and i think like i said i
can only speak of what happened to the
gym group and i'll probably use youtube
where people do
look on the staff board have a chat with
a staff from a heart you challenge what
you're charging and they're racing to
beat people in price
it's hard
seeing other people get clients maybe a
bit quicker than yourselves yeah um
especially you know you you can get the
same qualifications like i since my my
academy i haven't gained any
qualifications just my own research and
you'll find as you go along
you'll come across different ailments
illnesses and injuries if you'll go home
and you'll do your research on that and
once you've seen it when you sit once
you can then see it again from a mile
off yeah if you take it in
and then that is your own sort of you
make your own research yeah and that's
what can separate you because you know
but anyway so
i've i've seen people just get so
panicky about other pts lowballing it
and it's all been under the radar i've
even heard people charging 10 pounds
sure man yeah and
you sit there and you're like well no
one's gonna want to pay me my 30 or 40.
right
and it makes you
it puts you into a corner doesn't it
yeah yeah but just have that value in
yourself
and trust that you can deliver that
service
and just yeah i think the other thing is
as well like this is an industry where
you can make a decent living right
so
and when you're working those hours like
longer days longer hours whatever it
might be if you're charging 10 quid an
hour that's virtually minimum weight
you've got a lot more responsibility in
this job
this is not then
shelves and tescos yeah that's no
disrespect on someone who does that as a
job oh absolutely you're taking someone
else's health in your hands like someone
else's body in that session like
you know like you say you said
you're better off charging more and
giving a service because i think the one
thing that i've learned a lot from this
industry is people don't people invest
in you as a person
people invest in people
like if if you if you are training a
client and i've seen it the whole hour
repeats on the phone on facebook yeah
charging eighteen quid will you pay to
pay an eighteen quid a session you're
getting that's eighteen percent of the
session if you pay 36 for the session 40
quid a session whatever it might be
then
um
i think the other thing to you know
you've got there is
you give 100 to that client there and
then yeah you have like writing a
program like this is everything i think
for bts they forget um
say you were charging let's make this
you know whatever 40 quid an hour
or
say one session a week and a whole block
of sessions for a month it's 160
clickbait that's 960 equipment you're
popping no
dual tax
national insurance whatever your gym
rent situation have you got to pay that
yeah 24 7 contact support message of 7am
1am i'll say 1pm
p.m
you reply back to that this is time out
of your time like
you're not earning 40 quid for an hour
you know it's 40 quid for a week yeah
it's not just an hour yeah like you know
for many things so
i've been charging 10 pounds oh yeah
effectively once you've worked out you
know for 10 pounds in the gym and then
half an hour of nutrition half an hour
of like say program right and that's two
hours you've got a five pound now yeah
i can earn that doing a paper
yeah
i think that's the thing for me so like
i've done the aca and then like i've
kind of delved into more like
nutritional therapy naturopathy to go
down the nutrition route so that's come
through my own sort of stuff and that's
that's going to be dealing with a lot
more health issues but there is an
element that where i can bring that in
with the pt 100
but that's that's that's like getting a
lot more advanced but yeah like the aca
is probably a next step after you become
qualified the ac is a great one
i started to go down the snc route and
then quickly realized
this is just not the market northland
yeah no if you want to if you if you're
in loughborough or like london you can
and you want to work with athletes like
you definitely want to work with
athletes you're probably going to need a
uk qualification or something similar
right yeah but if you just want to work
with general population general public
the strength someone who wants to get
stronger who's that much whatever it
might be
strength and conditioning like it seems
great but it's just this is not the
market in my opinion in norfolk
i know what you're saying there's
certain things that you can apply to
general pop and tweak and change but
especially if you just get qualified in
snc you go to the athletes the athletes
don't come to you absolutely exactly so
yeah like i said if you're not in these
busy bigger cities
you've got to go find the work rather
than again like pt like you said people
think it's nine to five you can always
see
certain like there's always a few people
that come on the pt course i think right
but i charge 30 pound hours nine to five
and you see the cogs going yeah
eight hours a day yeah
obviously so i might be here to say 12
30 40 hours a day
that's not 14 ounces of pt yeah like i
think the max amount of sessions i've
ever hit in a week
forever probably maybe like 35 40
sessions yeah tomorrow i'm stunned i
probably averaged now about 30 sessions
a week right i think then i'm done yeah
you know because
a social life away from it and stuff
like this and like you say if you're
you're charging 10 pound an hour it's
1200 quid a month yeah you're not if
you're making like what 15 14 15 grand a
year um
like that you have not for that set
hours no not for the hours and and i
think the other thing that i've done
this year
is uh
out of out of like the hours that the
gym is open if someone wants to work
with me i charge over time premium i
charge more money because i'm like if
i'm here eight you know if you're eight
or nine at night
nine to 10 at night i'd be going
you know i've got misses at home if
you've got kids yeah you're not there to
put them to bed
you've got to make sure that you're
getting some value extra something extra
out of it just don't be afraid to
do that yeah because i don't think
people look two ways if the gym's got
people non-peak hours or if you're asked
to work overtime at any other job they
pay a little bit extra to make it worth
it even if you do night shifts or
whatever it's time and a half or
whatever
and pt's almost seem a little bit scared
to do this it's the same as like it's a
good angle it's the same as it's the
same as inflation like what's inflation
like two percent a year
comes back to january the first or maybe
if they do it by your tax year april 6
and people are going
i'll do a price increase but i'm scared
to email my clients
if you've given them decent quality
service for the last year
and they value your service and they
respect you as a person yeah as a
business then
you have you shouldn't have a problem
with doing it right and it's also
respect for yourself
um is the other one like if you're
educating yourself learning more and
you've learned you know you're giving
you've gained experience yeah if you're
upskilling then the price has to be
rather than that exactly like like also
i think that one for me is um
the fear and i think that's the thing
with a lot of people when i've had pj's
joined here working with jim like my gym
i've always said to him
oh where's your client oh they're not
end up they're just canceled you charge
me
uh i don't want to scare them off yeah
but if it was a hair appointment dentist
you'd be charged right so like i have a
cancellation policy in place because i
think the other thing is as soon as you
let someone off once or twice they think
it's easy and the problem is we know
we're getting the wrong thing
and the thing is what i was thought
about that in this industry we know that
i look at it this way so it's a bit of a
different angle but when someone's brand
new to join them a pt
they might be brand new to joining a gym
right because they go i don't know what
i'm doing i need a pt
if they've got an opportunity to get out
of that session because they're anxious
or they're nervous they will do yeah if
you turn around and go i'm going to
charge you for that they will turn up
because they go i'll be in charge yeah
in a way and that sounds like slightly
your bullying something but it's a
helpful way to get someone in the
environment and build their confidence
to make them more adherent actually it
seems weird to think of it that way but
it's investment isn't it and i think
that also ties into what you charge if
you charge someone 10 pound an hour
they're going to care about it 10 pounds
an hour
don't get me wrong i think some people
still have the idea but a lot of people
know however you can't just track money
at pt and then suddenly look good or
suddenly feel good
yeah we're here to help and we've got
the tools and the pathways you can go
down but the client still has to walk
those walks and we can help instill the
habits but if they don't do the stuff
that we recommend then changes don't
happen absolutely yeah well i'm sure
we've all had it numerous times i've had
it i've had it literally even recently
like client's got me talking about my
nutrition i'm like we've looked i've
looked at it twice
literally
i've made like basic changes right to
this person's diet and then they're
the person doesn't follow them and then
they say we're going to look at it and
i'm like okay what have you implemented
from the last thing this is basic stuff
10k 10 000 steps drink more water and
they've wanted to increase food so i'm
gonna increase literally the whole foods
you're eating xyz
they've done none of it and i'm going
why would i give you likes we'll call it
stage two if we don't stay there yeah
like yeah you know we're not gonna be
there to follow you if you're walking
down tesco's picking up cakes i'm not
going to suddenly go here and whack it
out your hand yeah i'm not following you
around
you have to take that ownership but
as a pt you can just do you can and i
think that's the other one isn't it like
we've all seen the mean is it the
and it's like when i'm not getting
results
and i'm playing on my personal trainer
pt's done you've done everything you can
as a trainer yeah and if that person is
still not following
you can't do anything no no no exactly
like
what do you do in that scenario so i
look i then look for damage limitation
i'm like all right
in their head they ain't ready to commit
to the nutritional cycle but they're
still turning up sessions willing to
throw around some weight so i'm like all
right
let's take care of that exactly yeah and
i'm thinking if they're if they're
throwing calories into their body you
know what they're probably going to get
strong yeah so let's let's get them
strong
that's a target they can achieve instead
of just thinking oh
they're not following their nutrition
they're not going to get no results no
find something that is measurable to
them in their headspace sometimes i'll
charge whatever for nutrition and
training if i've got a client who's
doing that i will be honest as a pt and
go look you're wasting
you're wasting me writing your nutrition
program right so why not take away the
nutrition and i'll reduce your feeling
it's a little bit it really it reduces i
haven't got excess work to do out of
here yeah so i'm like i'll help you out
you know you build then a better rapport
with that absolutely yeah yeah whereas i
know some coaches will there are coaches
out there who would literally go right
i'm not training you anymore yeah the
problem is they're actually instantly
just ruin someone's confidence
absolutely yeah
because that's it we all don't get tired
a little bit deeper like you said
because there might be other underlying
issues as to why they're not able to
commit to our stuff and it's
again that's why i think you're like
basically i think if you're going onto
that but definitely looking into like
mental side of things some you might get
someone to fill out a park q
i guarantee ninety percent of people
aren't on the park you know
there's a lot of reasons
disorder yeah they've literally just met
you for the first time you think they're
going to walk in some people will but
some people aren't going to go
anorexia
so if they've got an eating disorder and
you know about it start to work with
someone find a
you know psychiatrist or whatever it is
they might be
and link up with that person refer them
on whatever you know um i think that's
the thing i've seen before pts try to
do that job and i'm not you you can't
yeah
absolutely yeah that is not your skill
set yeah like you know if they've got it
and you know about it you need to refer
out like stop trying to be a a
i mean yeah
yeah like it's great to add strings to
your body but if you haven't got a
qualification yeah you're not good no
you're limited exactly stay in your lane
[Music]
you probably remember the client tom tom
right great guy yeah um
he
bless his heart i think he stayed with
me a lot longer than
what he needed to
because you know we had that rapport and
he was my day one client but he wanted
to get into strong man though around
some atlas don't you know do some really
heavy heavy stuff and i was like you
know what i like i can't facilitate that
yeah you know he moved on
um he's got another coach now as well
he's doing really well really really
well but that's
you got to understand that yeah you need
to stay in your lane yeah are you gain
more respect from a client for doing
that and what you then do is that
client's more likely to refer you onto
someone else but i've had clients coming
lately
i can stretch a client out or if a
client comes in with like say some
piriformis or whatever i can try some
glute activation work to see if it's
weak hip flexors and weak glutes because
they sit too much and stuff like that
and then a lot of the time my client
resolves the problem absolutely
sometimes it doesn't i'm not going to
keep going they keep coming into me
going i still got this i've still got
and i'm like right go see
we've exhausted our resources
i know this video i know this austria i
know whoever and i'll refer out to that
person because
i'm like i've tried the stuff i know
but you know i think we need this
clicking yeah i'm not doing that yeah
i'm not gonna try and click you're like
[Music]
but people doing it's just it's only
really from the same thing we probably
all have the getting into industry
because you want to help people yeah
you've got to be mature enough to
understand absolutely
there was both ways that i've had like
uh when i first you know many years ago
she now works here janine
yeah didn't eat any massage sports
massage and stuff
i remember when
i i referred a couple of people to her
and i one day had someone message me and
say oh i've been referred to you because
i need a pt and janine's referred me on
it works both ways yeah if you remember
a small therapist or whatever they will
probably start to refer back to you and
online
what a great way to build connections
exactly
brilliant especially do it in your own
gym as well if you can yeah like you
know if you can refer to someone in your
own gym great keep it in-house yeah
absolutely that's perfectly yeah yeah it
always comes back to being that client
building trust because they're like oh
yeah dom respects me enough to know what
he knows and what he doesn't know and
he'll send me to the right people yeah
yeah like you said that is where if you
do it right you get your referrals and
you pass your marketing done then isn't
it you haven't got to worry about
throwing up posters post on social media
necessarily every day is your soul
reliance
massive yeah i think yeah that's the big
one also
don't be that pt that has an answer for
everything
yeah it's okay
first few years of coaching
oh i wanted to know everything my ego
wouldn't dare let me say oh i don't know
that one no i have to know everything i
think that comes that will come with
maturity absolutely
absolutely
learn from that absolutely how good does
it look to a client in my opinion if you
go on oh i'm not too sure on that give
me a week i'll go research it or i'll
i'll go research it they're now not
paying you extra money you're going the
extra mile out of your way there's your
value there's a service there's the
value bank straight
and that person is going to go oh man
this person is serious about what they
do because they actually want to help me
rather than just going i'm not too sure
sorry yeah your hours up i'll see you
next week yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah exactly yeah like yeah too right
but
yeah how did you guys get on picking up
your first few clients when you
got qualified so i think we all did the
same thing go into these higher football
games
what were the tactics you've got when
you're right this is my first shift i
don't got any clients what do i do now i
made up a class
a voluntary random class i call it beach
bodies yeah
large bodies yeah and i gave my time for
absolutely free
12 whole weeks
and it got so good so popular
that the gym ended up saying right well
we'll take that class on as running as
one of our own and i got paid 20 pounds
class for that and then from there
i took on clients
yeah i uh i think i don't say i didn't i
um i i've done a lot of talking yeah
meet and greet like when someone comes
in through the pods or whatever it is at
the gym groups and the pure gyms
you say hello
smile
once someone's on a machine i was doing
like um
you know just chatting to them yeah just
literally seeing how they are like not
trying to sell my services say hello be
be that person there for that um person
and then i think i started to do some
like three 30 minute sessions yeah this
is what pt entails it's not going to be
a case of just annihilating youtube you
can't walk and you're whatever that's it
yeah yeah yeah if people get scared they
go oh please don't annihilate me take it
easy on me you know so um i think i've
done some free sort of 30 minute
sessions the main one was just chatting
to people yeah um i think now actually
one of the one of the big ones for me
and i know you kind of need to have some
testimonials and stuff once you've got a
few
then you've done the picking up and
you've spoke to people
excuse me get a website
right
many people go to me
how much do you get from your website
and i'm like i probably get 80 to 90 of
business from my website wow like it's
mad but i suppose i train most of my
people are 35 onwards right
um
and
they will go to google personal channels
and knowledge personal changes norfolk
bang whatever comes up i don't know
about you guys but if i find someone on
google maps and i click on their thing
and it this is me personally
say it's another business sells it for a
cake maker or a hotel b i don't know
what it is
if i click on it and it's got number
maybe email address not a website i'm
going
yeah but if you can slap a photo of that
person up as well yeah i know that
sounds stupid but some people aren't
done they will go that person's name is
say pick a client of mine say like mandy
mandy bush right if you put a person's
form with mandy bush or or or uh
caroline calgary or ben weave or
whatever it might be
they'll go that's what he looks like
that's his name bang facebook or
instagram are they on there then they'll
go on there and if you go on there
they'll that person might say like
checking dave with donald pt yeah this
is a legit testimonial this isn't
this is social proof this person exists
so this pt is legit he's got these
testimonials they're real people
because it's so easy to just get your
family to set up a google account called
wendy and put a review on it literally
leave a google review yeah
right it's so easy to do it so if you
can make it genuine stuff like that
that's that's a good one so for me like
once you've got your first view
like get a website
just wins cheap one whatever but then
yeah definitely like set up a class if
you're into that
i've done some classes like for the
three and you pick up client sonic
because again it's that people go this
is great but
what if i want to get stronger
absolutely
i want to like get lean
i know this is great but how do i make
it specific to me
classes classes are generic they will
limit you yeah exactly yeah i think a
big part of that as well as people want
to get to know you before they challenge
you spend an hour with you
yeah because at the end of the day most
general pop people we are going to apply
similar principles but you are gonna
spend one two three four hours a week
with this person and if they're a bit
dead or your personalities don't match
up and you don't look forward to that
hour or you just sat there like all
right 12 reps done 60 second rest and
you stand in silence yeah that's not fun
for them
i think that's one of the things you do
best beard is you make the sessions
enjoyable your clients are always happy
and smiley and yeah cause they get more
rest time because we're too busy
when that happens and you start to get
to a bit of a conversation with someone
else talking about their weekend you go
okay just do another set yeah you know
you probably you tend to do it on the
heavier stuff anyway yeah oh
it is strategic by the way
i've done it with all my clients like
you then get to your hour
and you run over like 10 minutes and the
client's going i'm really sorry i've
took an extra 10 minutes of your time
and i'm like so great we had fun right
like we enjoyed ourselves i don't know
about you i literally my my
initial consultation or my initial meet
and greet with someone that wants to
hire me i tell them straight and all my
clients will tell you this
life my motto is life is too short to
worry about five or ten minutes oh man
in this industry yeah man
you need to give the extra five or ten
minutes when when the opportunity occurs
yeah and i'm don't back to back four or
five clients all in a row give yourself
15 20 30 minutes to
get one run over or someone comes in
early to have a quick chat with them and
see if their day's been i've also like
say if i've had clients who you know
been doing long enough now that you get
your client come in and they're having a
crappy day and they're not as talkative
and you go let's go in the kitchen grab
a coffee and have a chat they need 10
15.
and then they go you go back into the
gym they feel so much better and they go
and they go right we better crack on so
we've got 45 minutes and you got 90 i've
got half an hour after you until the
next one so we can run over yeah yeah
yeah yeah and and that again that person
is going oh what a decent comparison and
that puts the person with personal
training that's basically it you're
basically yeah like you're basically
building that rapport with that person
and i think the other one as well when i
first started the journey
i had this guy what did he say it was
like the pt in shorts this guy never
wore trousers
and he came to he kind of done like a
run round of how to use all the techno
gym or whatever gym equipment it was
life fitness whatever it was in the gym
room and uh he was like he'd done it for
all of the gym groups and he was a pt as
well and um he basically said to us like
one of one of the best things you can do
is
make your pt's
clients like a lot of them will become
your friends
and i i took away from that i watched a
lot of the other pts then try to make
them their clients their friends
and i was like this is just a way of you
trying to keep them in your pocket to
get paid i'm like you don't do that
i'll honestly say i've got a lot of my
clients who are now actually friends
like
but you know i buy a birthday present
they'll buy me whatever you know we go
out to gigs together you know and it's
not like something can't do
because i'm like back at the key that's
going to keep them on board it's just
because actually you just built such a
good friendship
technically how was you and me yeah yeah
you were a client you said you know and
then
yeah
so it's just like yeah um but this i
remember the guy at the end of it he
said yeah one of my clients gave him
like an eight grand beamer
for christmas
but like yeah like you might build on
connections and you get all purchased in
life yeah you know
we went on holiday me and mrs too in
italy and uh in italy and one of my
clients had a friend we worked with and
they got to discount he got a discounted
rate that they're like
hotel that was like b and b in the
middle of the arsenal of nowhere in this
italian countryside
of the job yeah but like yeah like you
say if you go in and you've got like
no personality
and i think that's the other thing
don't just talk about fitness with your
clients no it's not always about that if
they like cars and you like cars go you
talk about gigs music concerts food
drink like don't be like i'm a pt i
never drink yeah don't be a writer don't
yeah
because your advice isn't going to be as
empathetic but they're not going to
relate to it i've got plenty of like
bottles of wine and i'm like oh i like a
glass of red wine bam there's a 25 pound
bottle of red wine for me for my
birthday and i'm thinking
yeah okay they're even telling me what
to have it with don't just chug it away
like
this it's just a nice perk of the job
like yeah yeah but again that's that's
where those people are actually they
respect you and what you do and they
know what you're doing if any of my
clients are watching and don't know i do
like coconut lattes
and an eight gram beamer
i've got
[Laughter]
[Music]
many years ago it would have been for
spray paints
sometimes
but yeah like you've got to have
you've got to have that relationship
with people and like
i'll do it like we i mean my clients
will go for like a meal of christmas
it's a bad idea because everyone just
rips the piss out of you as a pt yeah
you know what you've got you just opened
yourself up for trouble right now like
yeah and
christmas just gone
yeah it was it was brilliant yeah i had
11 people turn up
it was mad and there was already like 10
or 15 of the people doing the trampoline
anyway
um yeah
that was a good laugh
yeah i think that's the thing i think i
think one of the other things i've
always taken is um look after the people
who look after you and your business 100
yeah and respect them as much as you
want them to respect you
like if you're late five minutes in you
carry over the five minutes clearly yeah
yeah yeah you know yeah how it is and
then you just save the next one sorry
i'm right here like luck that's yeah i
set them ground straight away yeah
life's too short to worry about five for
ten minutes yeah right so
yeah so i think that's a that's a big
thing to think about yeah and like i
said you do come across a fair few
clients who are great because they can
train in those gaps which isn't morning
lunch and evenings they own their own
business show that love back to their
businesses as well even just like little
things like one of my main clients david
he's a hairdresser down on bursary he's
got a salon mom goes to get a heck up
there and it becomes more of a
absolutely
yeah yeah
i'll go get my haircut with him now yeah
yeah he was a client first
told me that he's a barber
i now go there yeah exactly yeah
yeah i think bro
yeah so that's uh
community network yeah it's it's exactly
it so same as i said about therapy so it
works it works both ways massively
nice i think how do you guys do at the
time
yeah obviously that's wrong i was going
to say
i was like huh it's not right but yeah
like
yeah what would you guys say looking
back if you could speak to your former
selves getting started out
what sort of advice would you give to
like either keep doing what you were
doing push harder on it or avoid certain
things
because i'm always like because
obviously it turned out right if you
both passed in the directions you went
down and didn't go badly
i think like yeah
that's all
do you know what
my biggest regret was trying to be
someone i wasn't and also
trying to train someone
how i
personally train as in like my own
training so i was i come into this this
industry with a bodybuilding centric
style of training
and what i wanted to do was just sculpt
certain areas of my body
and
i only followed that method with all my
clients
but your clients are so individual yeah
every now and then you'll get you'll
you'll attract the type of people who
want to look like you yeah because
they're like okay i appreciate his work
whatever i want to look like you i don't
mind doing what you do what
one rule doesn't work for everyone
and you've got to adapt that and my
biggest thing was
when i realized people didn't want to
train the same way as me
i was a little bit lost
and i found it hard
to adapt my passion to a different style
of training and then i had to
you know really evolve in that way and
mature
but also i got to a point where i'd see
other pts in the gym doing really really
well i go through a dry patch and i'd
want to copy what they're doing yeah and
you're not them no you're not them and
what i would have said to my
my younger self is
stick
to my own
ethics my morals of
delivering my service instead of trying
to copy and mimic
you know you can pick up great traits
from others absolutely you know network
and improve your skill set but don't try
and copy no
be individual yeah just learn your
clients because i think we all came into
this like i said in our 20s mostly just
vanity-based reasons wonderful
absolutely
absolutely at the end of the day you'll
get people like that come through but
but when you get like the mum of three
and a 40s come through you've got to
appreciate them they've got a very very
different life and even though it's not
yours you've got to learn about it and
you've got to ask me yeah yeah yeah i
think now i don't think i've got any
kind
who
wants to be
summer shred i
i know it's still around but i feel i
feel 90 of that is like that's like so
2010.
that era of fitness is gone we're moving
so much more to just general health
looking performance
yeah performance-based strength based
but also just looking at yourself like i
think my top of my head regret i would
have is as much as i'd done it for me if
i was competitive as a kid i would like
to compete in something and do sports i
think the biggest
it wasn't the only reason i did it i
didn't do i needed something for my
fitness career i needed to train for
something
it was the
thinking that
competing was going to make my pt career
fly oh that was everyone i
riches i've watched jamie overton yeah
and they basically had
well j mildred really well he basically
like youtubed his first competition and
from that and he then you got qualified
as a pt and from doing that competition
he become he's become a really
successful pt and now he obviously just
does like fulfillment right yeah um
and i thought
this is gonna be it it was the worst
eight months of business for me
because i was so worried about myself my
competing my food
i was tired i'm having to sit down on a
bench
whilst my diet client deadlifts
because i'm so tired and i'm trying to
preserve energy for my own training
session and i'm thinking
keep going keep going i finished those
eight months and as soon as i finished
and i started eating again
and
my energy came back and my my
my bloody actually personality came back
my clients actually started to like me
again yeah yeah
eight months yeah you know i compete in
whatever was fun it was a great
experience but if you literally think
that competing is a good idea
and also that's the other thing is as
well no i know but the other thing i
don't even know is i've never heard i
think
all my clients now i think
half of them don't even know i get like
one of them one or two will come in and
say yeah he's competing don't bring this
up
but sometimes it does go the other way
and yeah people often yeah well that's
it that's what i was going to say like
when people like
look at the pt if you're in like
stupidly good shape that can be off
playing man because someone goes they're
going to make me try and look like that
[Music]
i think the big one nowadays
getting stronger
confidence booster especially for
females
oh i love that yeah you know showing
them their true potential yeah exactly
you know showing them they can pick
men's artists
um i think that's a big thing now like
not yet
you know moving on like i said moving
away from the let's get summer shredded
yeah give us progress pictures are yeah
yeah i like this in 12 weeks okay what
happens after 12 weeks yeah yeah yeah
just go about the rest of the year the
rest of your life yeah training for
longevity
how did you feel the first 12 weeks i
remember i think it was just as i was
going on before you went i remember you
like you're going to start from huddled
up to a radio freezing cold on a summer
day because you were so i remember
breaking it yeah yeah
i literally did i turned this radiator
up so much but i snapped the adjuster
cap on and this thing was at six
yeah
and then it was sunk oh i was the only
one in there who was in there like this
is lovely everyone else was coming
everyone else
grabbed their stuff
like leaving the door to just get all
this hit out of this room but yeah like
i was i i was i loved summer i know so
yeah but yeah it's uh
that was probably my regret my regret
was thinking that that was going to be
my thing and then once i finished
competing
i had my best year after that 2016
because everything went back into the
business the focus and i'm not going to
sit here and say it was actually the
competition photos that they've done
it wasn't it was it was because my focus
was back on building my business and
focusing on my clients and
exactly that was it i think it's what i
think until you actually go through it
and do these aggressive like diet down
faces where you do get
un like unrealistically lean yeah you
don't realize everything else that comes
with it like sex drive dips the brain
fog and the attention span
people irritable i am lucky my my now
wife back then my message i'm lucky
secretly i'm going to propose in new
york because you probably have eight
months of being literally yeah to the
point where like and this is why i won't
die at clients like that now i won't do
it
because
i was at the point where you moved my
phone from like there to the other side
of that speaker
and i'd like be like why'd you move my
phone
[Music]
it but if i could go back
i think i'd i think i'd still do it
again yeah because it's a i love it if
you have those stories to tell i love
you
and you can't show people how to tell
how not to do exactly yeah so it's
it's a big thing so yeah the funniest
thing is i think all the times i've ever
tried to get stage ready it was three
times in my life
and i think every single one of them has
either finished in a relationship or
single
yeah because it takes a toll it takes
massive talk
absolutely it's a big thing so
it's tough i get it unfortunately you're
you if you want to be a coach when you
go down that avenue
sure fine but as uh if you want to be a
coach who coaches we'll call them
physique competitors that's anything
from bikinis and
um men's physique always bodybuilding
make sure you i know you don't have to
be
a decent basketball player to
coach basketball very well like
halfway will be honest as coach we know
he's strong australian strength coach
but he's not as strong as half of the
answer right
i
that only time when that twists from him
flips is if you want to have someone
else compete and get stage me
okay now i've experienced it and i know
how far because you also can help them
tap into the mentality you need to do it
but make sure they're in a decent place
as well yeah yeah
i think it all feeds back to like what
helps you all now is like having these
long old days running your own
businesses and then fitting the fitness
in on the side because like i know for
me at least when i got into fitness and
i was in my teens 20s i had to worry
about going to sick form
work done which
happened and then trained and that's it
mum dad couple meals yeah sometimes i've
gotta get takeaway every now and again
yeah that was it like why can't
[Music]
human biology that would have been
beneficial in this job like now i'm just
like i literally flunked it and i was
too busy going to the gym i was just
jimming i was doing whatever i was like
this is this is great i know you say
five six times a week cricket or
football saturdays and sundays at the
weekend
i now train two to three times a week
because
i just there's other parts of life
i'm doing my call i'm doing my course so
that's like pretty much a full-time
course around pt in 30 sessions a week
and owning a gym doing 60 hours of just
being here a week right and my wife
would like to see me yeah so
when all that's going on i'm showing you
five times a week i just ain't got the
energy to do that yeah it's stress so
like you have to think of think about
the client individually you can't put
every single day i'm sure we've all had
it how many times have you eaten our
training yeah yeah yeah that's normally
the first or second question tell me
what you do tell me your life what are
you doing i'll cop yet yeah yeah and
then it's basically how many times
how many times i would say to people how
many times a week can you minimum
definitely get in here don't say four i
write your program for four and you come
in two yeah because
calories or the nutrition might not work
if you're doing the calories or if
you've set them on a certain amount of
food and you're already training two
times a week on four and they're only
getting five thousand steps on ten and
they're not losing weight you that's
where it's your fault as a coach because
you actually might need to ask the
question of how many times can you
definitely get it i can always commit to
two right
and that's without sacrificing sleep
stress work relationships everything
else because these people might say like
oh yeah i can do five days a week and
they might do five days a week for a
couple weeks and then it is the sleep
that falls apart or the families and the
relationships that they get neglected
about trying to pull it back again as
well yeah so yeah that's that'll be
that's another one for me but yeah yeah
i know for me when i started it was just
like focusing on you go through of
course that right
calories go up or down if we get bigger
or smaller and then we progressively
overload to get stronger and it's so
easy to get stuck and i did for a while
to just look at those numbers but right
yeah last week was six reps today seven
last week was 50 kilos today she becomes
computerized don't you yeah yeah yeah
yeah that's not all it is some people
sometimes people just want to come in
and blow some steam they want to do it
off slam talking
a little free-for-all yeah yeah exactly
and it's hard to
or it's easy to fall into like i said
being a robot and just following those
numbers
especially as being a good coach like
the typical
i was supposed to get eight today you
only got seven like you did last week
and instantly a coach will just go
what have you done right rather than
has anything been off plan yeah because
as soon as you say what have you done
right you're accusing someone of doing
something wrong that person might have
had a really stressful day at work kids
kept them up at night you need to just
ask the question in a different manner
that the client is going to go
okay they've made me feel better that i
didn't hit that number
of them being like you have to
is the main thing like my clients are
always sick to death with me hearing
because every single session is how's
your food and sleep being recently yeah
right if someone comes in and then
feeling off or not quite doing right you
eventually come around
if you ask or whether they tell you like
oh yeah i did only get four hours sleep
last night
or whatever it's like well that's
that's fine we're hitting those numbers
today and we hit those numbers last week
when you're off all night sleep you're
still here yeah we're just ticking boxes
today
yeah certainly yeah so yeah man
nice um what would you guys do
say you were in my position now like
either teaching other students or you
being a student what would you want
added to the course to help because we
were saying obviously phil did a great
job i think i probably learned the most
on the business course um yeah that was
a big one the coaching and nutrition
were great don't get me wrong it was
definitely a lot more in depth but i
definitely found like setting up hmrc
and basics of like understanding the
client yeah
what did you guys found you sort of
learned the hard way you had to go seek
out yourself once you look at pt
i think
and there's that security yeah it's
quite nice um
business is a big one but i think
sometimes with the business things
people will focus way too much on like
blasting ten pound uh
every three days or something on a
facebook ad yeah
and there's so much of it now and you
can't compete with the bigger companies
who are blasting 50 a week
you
basically just get washed away yeah
um i think the business thing would be
one but like i'd be saying let's hope
you set up a website the basics when you
say tax like something like
teaching someone to actually just save
some money each month because they
totally i opted to forget you've got to
pay tax on the 31st of january and they
get this tax dollar and they're going
i've got an output on the direct debit
that costs you more money like um i
think another one would be once you've
got yourself going
i always like to say and the thing that
the pandora's taught us is now
try to have five to six months worth of
your minimum wage you need to live that
doesn't mean you can buy takeaways and
stuff like that that's basic stuff right
have five to six months worth of five to
six months worth of that money all
together in a savings account you need a
backup plan security plan yeah
um if you get injured
yeah yeah even just people on holiday
don't they and you've got to account for
that that's delays your paychecks i'll
fall into that trap when i get qualified
where you are right i'm doing 20 30
sessions a week
times out week by four times up by 12
past me yearly incomes like people are
ill people go on holiday you get or you
go on holidays
as well now and the gym doesn't actually
make money right so it pretty much
breaks itself even just about sometimes
i have to put my money in
so some people go that's not actually
that efficient but it's nice to have my
own place
rescheduled but like
i was like okay i'm off for 10 days it's
fine i can chill okay there's 10 days
i'm not earning any money it's 10 days
i've got to pay the other guys who work
here to cover the hours i would normally
do
i'm like oh this isn't great when you
think about it like i'm not going to
don't stress over it don't do sleepovers
but i would say make sure that you get
taught
a little bit more about the business on
just how to like yeah be a sense of the
realistic side of business i think
that's why you don't charge 10 an hour
because percentage of that hourly rate
is your pension is your holiday is your
single pay because we don't get that
otherwise i think people sometimes
assume that it is just like
a job but yeah exactly that's it like
you know like say certainly the holiday
one's a massive one yeah like i think
pt's i know some beauties take quite a
lot holiday but i don't take
i probably go i have to take two full
weeks off
like if we go to japan this year that'll
be two four weeks right and then i might
take and then after that it's like two
or three days around christmas two or
three days around new year
birthday yeah that's it yeah that's
pretty much me done yeah so i don't take
what is it 28 i don't get like 28 days
or whatever as most companies will get
paid or whatever it is we go get paid
for that stuff so you have this is where
like you think about what you're
charging yeah so i think
definitely what you say that i think the
business one integrating bit marketing
and
charging how much to charge yeah and
helping them just helping like pts or
train epgs learn why
do an example of say like 40 quid if you
charge that like we'll say for one
session with nutrition so that's another
half an hour home and a training plan
that's an extra half an hour so it's 20
quid for the 12th but then teaching them
your tax
your
national insurance yeah your what's the
other one um
because
that's a big one
um think that that section would be nice
to get that covered yeah uh it's just
teaching them that this you know you
value your worth yeah yeah so
um that would be the big one for me
how are you bid
to be fair i'd agree 100
um
diary as well
yeah diary because
yeah
as a self-employed individual you go
where the money goes like you know we
joked earlier about them i never used to
be a morning person and then i got so
busy in the evenings the only
availability i had was the seven and
eight am so now i was like
and i say this to my clients so it makes
me laugh
i'm not a morning person but i'm a money
person so let's get up at seven and
let's get it yeah because you you've
gotta
you've gotta make that that sacrifice
because not everyone can feel those
lunchtime slots you've gotta be unless
you're unless you are
right at the top of your game in the
area you work
a lot of the times
if your diary is booked up in the
morning seven to nine and say we'll call
it like busy times like five
five till eight right if you're booked
up great you can probably then depict
when that crime goes in if you've got
those slots free you can't hit that
person and say right now i can only do
10 a.m if they then go elsewhere don't
be grumpy about it yeah
yeah you just didn't want to get up
early enough yeah but you didn't want to
work late enough yeah exactly like this
you didn't want to you wanted that
tuesday off all the time yeah and even
once they are booked in is just [\h__\h]
being there like five ten minutes before
like on time is late really where's pt
you've got to be there in the gym ready
with the programme set hopefully with
the equipment you are ready to go as
well so when they walk in that's what
they're paying for isn't it yeah i think
when i first started i worked
it's pretty much apart from like
holidays i pretty much worked seven days
a week for three years yeah just to
build everything up yeah and now i don't
work sundays yeah
um because it's the only day off you
have to have that you have to you have
to give yourself some slack but
like you know if if the gym is not too
far for you to travel
and you think i could basil two clients
nine till eleven on sunday and still
then go to the coast
go out for the day yeah
yeah it's not a bad bet you know
especially if you do that and you think
actually you know what sunday so on
social hours say like here the gym shot
they get in the gym to themselves as
well right i'm gonna charge time
and that's how you build up like you
said about five six months in the rear
so that if and when things do go quiet
because there are busier and quieter
times of the year you would not seem to
be about desperate pt running around
like my classroom waivers john sessions
do you want a session do you want a
session with my pitch let me train you
yeah yeah you see that as well yeah yeah
so that's i think they're the biggest
business stuff learning about business
and finances and just how much to charge
and those sorts of things
nice cracking i think that's good for us
guys
i appreciate you both taking time out of
your days and hopefully like i said i've
got guys coming through level two now
once it starts getting to a point where
they're towards the end of a level three
what you're hoping to do is set up this
network of role models like yourself so
then as and when they want to go see
what life is like as a real pt they can
you can be report call and
show them what the reality is like i've
sort of helped two or three people
before but i i'm not afraid to sit here
and say like i think both of us would
happily
have the ability to take on even for
yourself as well away from integrity but
as an adult all three of us could easily
take on like a mentorship role
oh
bt came to me after they're qualified
and said like you know can you help me
now with extra development in my
business i'd happily do that yeah you
know
the help from there but certainly like
yeah i think i think the main one for
most people like i could easily sort of
sit here and say about my own gym
but as a brand new pt industry with no
clients to come into my gym and chuck a
couple hundred quid at me i think
obviously the best route for most pts
would be budget gym yeah yeah because if
you can make it there you can make it
anywhere exactly if you can't make it
there yeah maybe pt's not you yeah and
it's one of those things but like we
probably all sought out automatically at
the time because of where we were what
we're doing but some people don't
naturally think to do that as well
that's why i want to start at least just
guiding people in the right direction
like oh what route do you want to go
down are you going to go more towards
like
like i said strength mainstream oh
here's so-and-so it doesn't have yeah go
look what it's really really like for a
day because it ain't like everyone put
on social media no no no no no in social
media
like i like you jordan shallow yes yes
muscle dark he's a good guy like guy's
like 270 pounds of just like
but
he's he's always on the move he's always
on the go and he's built a decent
business out of it he's pretty much a
lot of fun stuff but he does a lot of
like
seminars in like canada and he's did
like maybe dubai and the uk
and the other
but like you can see he's always
grinding he'll be up at like 4
30 2am or something stupid on instagram
and i'll see it when i go on the stomach
but
that's what's really nice yeah it's it's
what it is it's not um i think the issue
we get is we see the adverts become a
qualified pt and start grabbing your job
people go
sounds easy
i think i want to finish off was i had
like i had a i had someone who i worked
with and they said i'd love to do your
job and i was like oh really what's that
and it goes easy you just rock up and
train people yeah
i sat there and
wow
um to do that job yeah yeah yeah show me
where that job is yeah brilliant yeah
but yeah it's it's not like that but
the stuff you get out of it i i wouldn't
change it yeah
true yeah you can't buy that reward that
feeling you get when you train clients
exactly i know people who've gone oh you
know i shouldn't have done i shouldn't
have my bt and we always get frustrated
periods and stuff like that like when
pt's never done this with money it's
always going to go past is great if i
continue on this i'm earning like x
amount a year oh there goes a couple of
coins
and it's not always reflective of the
effort either
that's the big one there the fastest
thing i was going to say if you get a
drop off of clients
don't go on rubbish i'm going to publish
pt i shouldn't have done this this is a
point that's on track of my job you
don't know that person's circumstances
um so
you know
more will come around whatever it's it's
just it is what it is you always have
fluctuations and again that's why it's
essential to have that little bit of
savings on top of that
appreciate it boys